<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter directed to the Right Honourable the Earl of Perth, governour to the Prince</title>
            <author>Melfort, John Drummond, Earl of, 1649-1715.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 12 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47970</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1361</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC N18878</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18207840</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 18207840</idno>
            <idno type="VID">107119</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A47970)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 107119)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1127:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter directed to the Right Honourable the Earl of Perth, governour to the Prince</title>
                  <author>Melfort, John Drummond, Earl of, 1649-1715.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>11 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Charles Bill, and the executrix of Thomas Newcomb ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700 [i.e. 1701]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Royal arms on t.p.</note>
                  <note>Dated (p.3): Friday 18th of February, 1701.</note>
                  <note>"Asserting Louis XIV's willingness to provide military support for the Pretender's claims to the British corwn."--NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Formerly identified as Wing L1361 and M1642. Both numbers cancelled in Wing (2nd ed., 1994) due to post-1700 imprint date.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>James, --  Prince of Wales, 1688-1766.</term>
               <term>Louis --  XIV, --  King of France, 1638-1715.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  William and Mary, 1689-1702.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Kings and rulers --  Succession.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:107119:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 51 -->
            <p>A LETTER Directed to the RIGHT HONOURABLE THE Earl of Perth,
GOVERNOUR TO THE PRINCE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Charles Bill,</hi> and the
Executrix of <hi>Thomas Newcomb,</hi> deceas'd, Printers to the Kings moſt
Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Majeſty. 1700.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:107119:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 52 -->
            <head>Die Lunae, 17 Februarii, 1700.</head>
            <p>UPon Reading this day a Letter communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to the Houſe by
His Majeſties Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, Dated <hi>18th February, 1701,</hi> and Directed,
<hi>To the Right Honourable the Earl of</hi> Perth, <hi>Governour to the
Prince, Theſe,</hi> It is Ordered by the Lords Spiritual and Temporal in
Parliament Aſſembled, That the Lord Keeper of the Great Seal of
<hi>England,</hi> do give Order, that the ſaid Letter be forthwith Printed
and Publiſhed.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Matthew Johnſon, Cleric<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g>
Parliamentor<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g>
                  </hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:107119:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 52 -->
            <head>A LETTER Directed to the RIGHT HONOURABLE THE Earl of Perth,
GOVERNOUR to the PRINCE.</head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Friday</hi> 18th <hi>of</hi> February,
1701.</date>
               </dateline> 
               <salute>My D<hi rend="sup">st</hi>. B<hi rend="sup">r</hi>.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ince I promiſt to put in Writing what we had not time to
talk fully of, I am ſet down to it in the Morning, that my Letter may be
ready for the Meſſenger if any call.</p>
            <p>I told you all that I had heard at <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſailles,</hi> and
the favorable Audience I had of <hi>Madame de Mentenon,</hi> for which I beg it
of you to return my moſt humble Thanks to the Queen, and beg of her to be
ſo good as to Thank <hi>Madame de Mentenon,</hi> and know from her what can
be <pb n="4" facs="tcp:107119:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 53 -->done in that matter. It will
be a great Charity in the Queen.</p>
            <p>I told you amongſt other things the great Fleet the King
intends to put out this Summer, the Orders being given, and the Money ready,
the Stores full, and every one concerned Active in their Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; There is no
doubt but this Fleet will be Maſter of the Sea for ſome time, if not for
all the Summer, becauſe the <hi>Dutch</hi> dare not ſtir till the
<hi>Engliſh</hi> be ready, and they have long Debates yet before they can be
in a Condition to Act, if they have the Will; and it is a Queſtion if they
will have it at all.</p>
            <p>The King never had ſo favorable a Conjuncture, if he can
perſuade this King that his Affairs are really in the Circumſtances they
are in, but there is the Difficulty.</p>
            <p>The King and Queen have more Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority with the King, and with
<hi>Madame de Mentenon,</hi> than any other in the World can have, but that's
not all, there ſhould be ſome one Acceptable to the Miniſters, who
ſhould lay before them theſe Proofs, their Majeſties cannot enter into
the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tail of, and explain the Reaſons, make Plans and Memoires by their
Majeſties Approbation, to Convince them of the neceſſity, and to ſhew
the eaſineſs of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring the King, the Glory it brings to their King,
and the Advantage to Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:107119:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 53 -->
            <p>How this will be done their Majeſties are wiſe enough to
Conſider, and I think it is not a Subject fit for me to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter upon, but
their Friends in general, who know not the half of what I know in this matter,
think that it will not be well done by a Proteſtant Miniſter, Lazy in his
Temper, Enemy to <hi>France</hi> by his Inclination, Tainted with Commonwealth
Principles, and againſt the Kings Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning by any other Power than that of
the People of <hi>England,</hi> upon Capitulation and Terms, who is
ſuſpected of giving aim to the Compounders, if not worſe.</p>
            <p>That Mr. <hi>Carrell</hi> is qualified no man doubts, but in
Society with the other, theſe who muſt be Inſtrumental will not truſt
him as he ought, ſo that ſo long as the other is within diſtance of
penetrating the Affairs, they will never think themſelves ſecure.</p>
            <p>And yet the King has no ſuch Game to play as by theſe very
Perſons, who are thus defident, namely the true Church of <hi>England</hi>
Party, the Catholicks, and the Earl of <hi>Arran,</hi> and I ſhall ſay
ſomething as to every one of them. The King cannot but be ſenſible that
the true Church of <hi>England</hi> Party, and their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Head now the
Biſhop of <hi>Norwich,</hi> has been ſilent of a long time, and their
Majeſties may remember what weight the Court of <hi>France</hi> laid upon
their joyning <pb n="6" facs="tcp:107119:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 54 -->the King (I mean
the Non-ſwearing Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy) in caſe of a Landing.</p>
            <p>Therefore all arts ſhould be tried with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out delay to get them
to enter into Correſpondence again, and every Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diment ought to be
removed, I ſay with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out exception, and though ſometimes it is of hard
digeſtion for Soveraignes who ought to be obeyed without reſerve, to yield
to the humours of Subjects, yet Prudence ſhould teach them, when they cannot
without hurting their Affairs do what they would, to do what they can, and
remember the Fable of the Dog, who loſt the Subſtance for the Shadow.</p>
            <p>Aſſurances from the Non-ſwearers, the Soundeſt and
Venerabliſt part of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Church, would be of great uſe at
this time, to perſuade <hi>France</hi> to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take this great Affair, for
beſides their owne Example at a Landing, and their Preaching and Writing to
the People, that their Religion was in no danger, it is moſt certain they
know better than any others can, what the Church of <hi>England</hi> in general
would do for the Kings Service, and they being to run all the hazard, would be
better believed at the Court of <hi>France</hi> than any other, as I found by
experience.</p>
            <p>As to the Catholicks and others Aſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciate with them
unfortunately for the King they were thought to have too 
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:107119:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 54 -->much Inclination for me, and
ſo have been reckoned as uſeleſs to the King, but I muſt beg leave to
ſay, that Undertaking was the beſt Feather in his Wing, and was moſt
juſtly thought ſo by him, and by the Court of <hi>France</hi> too, even to
that degree, they pretended if this and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Article concerning the
Clergy, could be made Appear, they would Concur with the King to Invade
<hi>England.</hi> They Conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of Seven Regiments of Horſe and
Dragoons, their Arms, Trumpets, Kettle Drums, Standards, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> were
all ready, and are yet in ſurety, their Men were all Liſted, and their
Officers Choſen, and they had twenty Horſes to a Troop, which Troops lying
at a diſtance in a Horſe Country, twenty Horſes would ſoon have
Mount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the reſt.</p>
            <p>Thoſe who could not divine the Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and the Uſe of
the Undertaking, blamed the Raſhneſs of it, and even ſome Churchmen have
not been diſapproven for endeavouring undutifully (becauſe contrary to the
Kings Written Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders) to break the Deſigne; but I deſire you now for all
this to believe, that you have not ſuch another Argument to uſe to the
Court of <hi>France</hi> as this, and if you could make it appear, as it might
have been done ſome Years ago, I ſhould have very good Hopes of this
Summers Work. Nay let the King have what <pb n="8" facs="tcp:107119:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 55 -->other
Hopes, or even Promiſes you pleaſe from the Court of <hi>France,</hi> this
is to be Encouraged, and if poſſible, to be put in the Circumſtances it
was in, for if ever there be a Landing in <hi>England</hi> to purpoſe, it
muſt be before they can be armed, and they cannot be armed before the
Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment come to a Reſolution concerning the War, and conſidering the
few Troops in <hi>England,</hi> ſuppoſe theſe men to be no better than
Militia, what a Diverſion would it be.</p>
            <p>It is not neceſſary for me to ſay any more of this
Article, till I know whether their Majeſties have as good an Opinion of this
Undertaking as I have. If ſo I ſhall ſhew what I think to be done in it,
if otherwiſe I ſhall ſave the Pains.</p>
            <p>As to the Earl of <hi>Arran,</hi> it would be of great uſe to
have an Underſtanding with him. He will have none where— can prye; his
all is at ſtake, and he ought to be wary with whom he ventures to deal.</p>
            <p>I think it better for the Kings Service, that the Court Party
prevailed in the manner they have done in the Parliament of <hi>Scotland,</hi>
than that the Country Party ſhould have got their Will. Oppoſition ſwells
the Waters to a Flood, and ſo long as the Country Party is not diſcouraged,
they gain more Ground in the Kingdom than they loſe in Government. So that 
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:107119:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 55 -->the Diſaffection to the
Government will encreaſe, and one may judge of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in general, which
is of an other Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per than this pretended Parliament, or rather Presbiterian
Rabble, ill repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting the Nation. For ſince even in it, there is ſuch
a Struggle againſt the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, what would there be in a Free Parliament,
which the <hi>P.</hi> of <hi>O.</hi> durſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver hazard to call.</p>
            <p>The Nation then, at leaſt a great part of it, being
diſaffected to this Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, it is of the laſt Conſequence that E.
<hi>Arran</hi> may know what to do in caſe of an Invaſion of
<hi>England,</hi> or in caſe he and his Friends be obliged for Self
preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation to riſe in their own Defence.</p>
            <p>The Army who are and ever were well-affected, are to be gained
by Money, and a little goes a great way with them.</p>
            <p>The Disbanded Troops would be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged, and the Officers are
well inclined.</p>
            <p>The Places of Strength would be ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and ſuch as can be
put in Defence (without Expences) fortified.</p>
            <p>To do all this, at leaſt ſuch a part of them as can be begun
with, a ſmall Sum will ſerve, and He ought to have Hopes of it, and of the
Command.</p>
            <p>Theſe being only Heads to be diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of, and much to
be ſaid of every part, it is not to be thought that this Letter can carry a
final Concluſion; for it may <pb n="10" facs="tcp:107119:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 56 -->be
upon Diſcourſe, I might change my Mind, or be more confirmed in, and ſee
further.</p>
            <p>This makes me inſiſt again to you, upon two things as
appearing to me ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely neceſſary to put things upon a right
foot.</p>
            <p>The Firſt is the removing of all Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediments out of the way,
and ſending all Suſpected Perſons to <hi>Champagne</hi> or
<hi>Burgundy,</hi> according to their Gouſt.</p>
            <p>And the Second is of the laſt Uſe, both to their Majeſties
and the Prince, which is the Eſtabliſhing of ſuch a Number, under no
Qualification, to talk of their Affairs in their Majeſties Preſence, with
whom we can freely converſe and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe what may be for their Majeſties
Service.</p>
            <p>As for the Firſt, It will be for the Kings Reputation both at
the Court of <hi>Rome, France,</hi> and with all his true Friends in
<hi>England</hi> for many Reaſons—</p>
            <p>As for the Second, It is according to Scripture, In the
multitude of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellors there is ſafety.</p>
            <p>Nothing is ſo dangerous as firſt to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine what one will
do, and then hear Reaſons againſt it, and immitate the deaf Adder who
hearkens not to the Voice of the Charmer, let him Charm never ſo ſweatly.
Reaſons againſt a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution taken, offend, and the more 
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:107119:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 56 -->Force they have, they offend
the more, whilſt before the Reſolution be taken, Reaſon has its Effect,
and the Determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations are not the Effects of Humour and Faction, but of
Prudence and Juſtice.</p>
            <p>If in any thing I fail, I'le Swear its want of Underſtanding,
and not of Will. And I beg, that their Majeſties may be perſuaded, that it
is not Humour nor Vanity, but their Service I have in my viewe, who am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My D<hi rend="sup">st</hi>. B<hi rend="sup">r</hi>.</salute>
               <signed>Moſt humbly Yours.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>There are no Letters from <hi>England,</hi> I expect and am
promiſt—</p>
               <p>I forgot to tell you, that the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juncture ought to be
improven ſo long as the Court of <hi>France</hi> have the Ill Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the
Pr. of <hi>Orange</hi>'s Treachery diſcovered lately in their hands.</p>
            </postscript>
            <trailer>Superſcription, <hi>For the Right Honourable the Earl
of</hi> Perth, <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour to the Prince, Theſe.</hi>
            </trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
